Good morning. Today's דף Daf is כ"ו Chaf Vav (26), שם הוי"ה,
Shem Havaye, and we pick up on the bottom of כ"ה עמוד
ב', Chaf He Amud Bet, and we actually had one line left
that was the wrap-up of the previous סוגיא, Sugya, which I forgot
to read, so we'll start with that line.
And the previous סוגיא Sugya all had to do with this whole
question
about this אוויר ככלי דמי, Avir K'kli Dami, which is a fascinating
issue. The blood has to come straight out of the neck of
the animal into the vessel. So how come when it's passing, it's
not coming from the air into the vessel? Why is it considered
straight? And the idea is the airspace above it is considered like
the vessel itself. We applied that also to the water of the
חטאת, Chatas, whether that's for leniency or stringency, once it's directly over
the airspace, assuming the vessel's the bottom is still there. If the
bottom has fallen out, the גמרא Gemara sort of just concluded that
obviously, but it didn't explicitly say this, but the implicit message was
that obviously then the airspace would not be like the vessel if
the bottom has fallen out. And along the way, we dealt with
this principle that in the making of the gathering of the waters
of the
פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, you have to transfer to the vessel through
something that's not מקבל טומאה, Mekabel Tuma, as opposed to through something
that is susceptible, like a human hand or some other type of
a thing that's not a legitimate way to transfer the water into
the vessel for the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So wrapping that up,
the גמרא Gemara says the following. ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא, V'amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, this line starts with the word אבא, Abba,
it's about three, four, five, six, seven lines down in the wide
lines of כ"ה עמוד ב'. Chaf He Amud Bet. ואמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן מעדותו של רבי צדוק, V'amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, Me'iduso shel Rabbi Tzadok, from the testimony
of רבי צדוק, Rabbi Tzadok, נשנית משנה זו. Nishnishnu Mishna Zo. This
הלכה Halacha that I just mentioned about how the water gets to
the vessel,
we
can that's where this משנה Mishna is taught. דתנן, De'tenan, we taught
in the משנה Mishna in עדויות, Ediyos, so it's
מעדותו, Me'iduso, when they gathered up and they sort of created the
foundation of יבנה, Yavne, Rabbinic Judaism and so on and they got
everybody's testimonies of what the practices had been. So העיד רבי צדוק,
Heid Rabbi Tzadok, רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok testified על הזוחלין, Al Hazochalin,
the flowing waters, שקילחן בעלי אגוזים שהן כשרות, She'kilchan b'alei Egozim she'hen
k'sheros, if you sort of directed their flow with leaves
of nuts, which are not edible, so therefore they're not מקבל טומאה,
Mekabel Tuma, then that's valid. Okay. And but the point being, there's
two points: A, you're allowed to direct their flow in order to
gather them, but B, only if you use something like the leaves
of nuts, something that's not edible and not מקבל
טומאה. Mekabel Tuma. וזה היה מעשה באוחליא, V'zeh haya ma'aseh b'Ochalaya, this
happened in this place אוחליא, Ochalaya, ובא מעשה לפני חכמים, u-va ma'aseh
lifnei Chachamim, and it came, the case before the sages בלשכת הגזית,
be'Lishkas HaGazis, and this is the testimony because then this links us
back to the Temple period because here we are in יבנה Yavne
and so on. Anyway, and it came to the sages, the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin in the לשכת הגזית, Lishkas HaGazis, והכשירו, ve'hichshiru, and they said
that's valid. Okay, so that wraps up our previous סוגיא. Sugya. New
point.
אמר רבי זירא אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi Zeira Amar Rebbe, so said
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira in the name of רבי, Rebbe, הצורם אוזן
פרה ואחר קיבל דמו פסול. Ha'tzorem ozen parah v'achar kibel damo, pasul.
So since we're dealing with issues about קבלת הדם, Kabbalas HaDam, it
has to go into the כלי, kli, it can't hit the floor,
it can't hit the knife and from the knife go into the
vessel, it has to go straight from the neck of the animal,
that's the airspace discussion, so within this context of how you do
the קבלה, Kabbalah, we talk about the following thing, which is not
so much about the act of קבלה Kabbalah but something that takes
place during the process of קבלה. Kabbalah. If after the שחיטה, Shechita,
while the blood is in midair, you gotta love the way the
rabbis
are like
freeze-frame and are able to talk about it this split second, while
the blood is in midair after the שחיטה Shechita but before it's
been caught, somebody goes and punctures the ear of the dead cow,
of the head of the cow that's now been severed.
Okay. הצורם אוזן פרה ואחר קיבל דמו, Ha'tzorem ozen parah v'achar kibel
damo, and then you caught the blood. So the point is after
the שחיטה, Shechita, if it's before the שחיטה, Shechita, it's obviously a
בעל מום Ba'al Mum and it's פסול. invalid. But you puncture the
ear after the שחיטה Shechita before the blood was caught, that's also
פסול. invalid. פסול, Pasul, it's invalid. שנאמר: Shenemar: ולקח מדם הפר, V'lakach
mi'dam hap'ar,
you take from the blood of the ox, that's the דרשה drasha
we learned that you have to directly catch the blood from the
neck of the ox, or from any animal. פר היה כבר, Par
hayah kvar, so it's ה' Ha פר, Par, the ox, and the
ה', Ha, so before we learned that the ה' Ha comes to
tell you it has to be the lifeblood, but here the ה'
Ha is telling you that it has to be in the same
state it was before. It has to be without a blemish. And
therefore, when the blood is caught, the animal has to remain without
a blemish. Now, it's pretty hilarious, maybe that's not the right word,
but anyway, it is a little funny because the animal has its
head severed, so it's what more בעל מום Ba'al Mum do you
need than that? You got an animal with its head cut off.
And if you think about it, the head that is severed, now
you're making a hole in the ear. What about that gaping hole
in the neck? But the point is, is that the דרשה drasha
is other than that, sorry, like other than that, Mrs. Lincoln, how
was the show? Other than the fact that it's got this huge
hole in the neck, it has to be perfect. It has to
be without a blemish. So therefore, if you made a hole in
the ear, that's a blemish.
Monty Python, it's only a scratch.
All right, it's only a scratch. Oh, it's only a blood wound.
Okay, it'll get better. So
anyway, so if you bracket that, okay, other than the שחיטה
shechitah issue, okay, it has to still be unblemished, okay, when you
catch the blood. So that's הלכה. halacha. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says אשכחן קדשי קדשים. ashkachan kodshei kodashim.
That's the Holy of Holies because this is a weird idea that
תוספות Tosafot says normally we don't have to if something is true
by one קרבן korban we assume it by the others. Here the
גמרא Gemara has to say we take it by the חטאת chatat
and we apply it to the others. So תוספות Tosafot asks like
why here did we have to need a special פסוק pasuk to
extend this to other קרבנות korbanot we just wouldn't readily assume it?
But I think because it is such a bizarre idea, maybe we
want to say all right, maybe that's only by the Holy of
Holy sacrifices. קדשים קלים מנלן? Kodshim kalim minalan? How do you know
it applies even to like a שלמים? shlamim? אמר רבא Amar Rava
תניא tanya we taught by קרבן פסח korban pesach שה תמים זכר
בן שנה יהיה לכם. seh tamim zachar ben shanah yihiyeh lachem. Okay,
a perfect sheep, male, one year old, it shall be. Okay, and
the פסוק pasuk right before it is תכסו על השה. tachossu al
haseh. You shall שחט shacht the קרבן korban based on the family,
the בית אבות. beit avot. And then שה תמים יהיה, seh tamim
yihiyeh, so after the תכסו, tachossu, even after the שחיטה, shechitah, שה
תמים, seh tamim, it has to be perfect. Okay, the previous פסוק
pasuk talked about שחיטה shechitah and here it's saying unblemished, okay, and
that's a פסח pesach which is קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. שיהיה תמים
ובן שנה, Sheyihiyeh tamim uven shanah,
so it has to remain unblemished and one year old בשעת שחיטה
בקבלה. bish'at shechitah bekabbalah. Okay, you know even after the act of
even after בשעת שחיטה בקבלה. bish'at shechitah bekabbalah. Okay,
at the time of שחיטה shechitah and at the sort of catching
of the blood. So even at that stage it has to remain
perfect. So the גמרא Gemara says בהולכה ובזריקה מנלן? beholacha uvezrikah minalan?
Okay,
how do you know about when you're carrying it and you know
transporting it it has to remain perfect? I just want to see
how do they how do they punctuate this? Do they have the
comma after after שחיטה shechitah or the comma after בקבלה? bekabbalah? I'm
curious because logically it should say yeah no they have it at
the comma after after שחיטה, shechitah, which is the way the grammar
reads, but it's funny because it's not just that it has to
be תמים tamim בשעת שחיטה. bish'at shechitah. Okay, anyway, maybe that's the
point. שה תמים זכר בן שנה יהיה לכם. seh tamim zachar ben
shanah yihiyeh lachem. So first we read תכסו tachossu that it has
to be perfect at the time of שחיטה. shechitah. And then the
point is בקבלה בהולכה ובזריקה מנלן? bekabbalah beholacha uvezrikah minalan? So that's
only at the time of yeah I think that I'm sorry, that's
how I would read it. Okay, so it says
פסוק pasuk is תכסו tachossu which equals שחיטה shechitah על השה. al
haseh. And then it says שה תמים
זכר בן שנה יהיה לכם. seh tamim zachar ben shanah yihiyeh lachem.
So
here
we have the תכסו, tachossu, the שחיטה, shechitah, it has to be
תמים tamim and זכר zachar and בן שנה. ben shanah. How do
you know that not only at the time of שחיטה shechitah but
even afterwards? So I would sort of assume since it says this
after the שחיטה, shechitah, it means that even after the שחיטה shechitah
it has to remain that way. But that's not רבא Rava is
not saying that. He's saying the פשט pshat is that it's just
at the time of the שחיטה. shechitah. How do you know to
extend it beyond the time of the שחיטה? shechitah? So, בקבלה בהולכה
ובזריקה מנלן? bekabbalah beholacha uvezrikah minalan? How do you know to extend
those requirements even when the blood is caught and transported and thrown?
תלמוד לומר יהיה. Talmud lomar yihiyeh. כל הוייתו לא יהיה אלא תם
ובן שנה. kol havayato lo yihiyeh ela tam uven shanah. The יהיה
yihiyeh means all of the things you're doing to make it a
כשר kosher קרבן, korban, at all the stages, not just at the
שחיטה shechitah says at all the stages you need those requirements to
be satisfied. Now what רבא Rava has done is he's not only
extended it to a קדשים קלים kodshim kalim because of this פסוק
pasuk by פסח, pesach, he's extended it not just to the catching
of the blood but also to the transporting and the throwing, right?
The first statement was only learning it from the catching, the ולקח
מדם הפר, velakach midam hapar, which is at the catching it has
to be it has to be perfect. This יהיה yihiyeh is saying
at all stages the requirements remain. And that's going to get us
into a little bit of trouble. So let's take a look. Okay,
כל הוייתו לא תהא אלא תם ובן שנה. kol havayato lo tehei
ela tam uven shanah. איתיביה אביי Eitivei Abaye so אביי Abaye challenged
this. רבי יהושע אומר Rabbi Yehoshua omer כל הזבחים שבתורה שנשתייר בהן
כזית בשר או כזית חלב. kol hazvachim shebatorah shenishtayer bahen kezayit basar
o kezayit chelev. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said that there's a requirement
that when you throw the blood,
that there still be the flesh and the fat of the animal
still remain. Even though the blood is what atones and is the
only thing that determines the כשרות kashrut of the קרבן, korban, the
validity of the קרבן, korban, nevertheless, when the blood is thrown, it
can't be that you know that the meat and the fat and
whatever have all been destroyed or all become טמא tamei and so
on. Okay, so so he says, now what if most of it
has been destroyed or טמא tamei and a little remains? According to
this opinion, okay, this is only within רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua opinion
that demands that there be blood and fat to remain in order
to be able to throw the blood of the קרבן. korban. Okay,
so it says, so רבי יהושע אומר Rabbi Yehoshua omer כל הזבחים
שבתורה שנשתייר בהן כזית בשר או כזית חלב. kol hazvachim shebatorah shenishtayer
bahen kezayit basar o kezayit chelev. As long as any little thing
remains, yes, I require it to remain, that's his first חידוש chiddush
number one. It's not enough that it's just the blood that is
present, the meat, meat and fat has to be there or fat
has to be there when you're throwing the blood, but doesn't have
to be all the meat or all the fat. Even if what's
only left is a כזית kezayit an olive's worth of the meat
or an olive's worth of the fat, זורק את הדם zorek et
hadam that's sufficient to throw the blood. And even if the rest
of it has been destroyed or has become טמא tamei and so
on. Now the problem is, is that if we're saying כל הוייתו,
kol havayato, which is not only at the time of שחיטה shechitah
but also at קבלה, kabbalah, הולכה, holachah, and זריקה, zerikah, right, that's
part of what רבא Rava is adding, so if the זריקה zerikah
has to be perfect, meaning it has to be unblemished, well, if
if if all of the fat and the meat is destroyed except
for a כזית, kezayit, it's not unblemished, something has happened to that
animal. So how does that work according to him? You see it's
not true that it doesn't has to be unblemished at the time
of the זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait
where are we? תרגומה
בבן שנה. Targuma ben shana. So גמרא Gemara says fine, we got
to pull back a little bit. When רבא Rava says that this
פסוק pasuk here tells you all of the stages, okay, and he
learns it by קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, this יהיה yihyeh is really
going to be interpreted only relating to the word that it comes
most immediately juxtaposed to the בן שנה. ben shana. What we're going
to say is the following: the requirement here of the פסוק pasuk
of
ולקח מדם הפר, velakach midam hapar, okay, and the ולקח velakach here
means, right, what does the ולקח? velakach? The ולקח velakach here means
קבלה, kabbalah, okay, that the קבלה kabbalah has to be unblemished, it
still has to be הפר. hapar. That's true for that idea of
תמים tamim בשעת, bish'at, that's תמים בשעת קבלה. tamim bish'at kabbalah. And
that applies by all קרבנות, korbanot, okay, even by קדשים קלים kodshim
kalim or whatever. But this פסוק, pasuk, right, of יהיה yihyeh that
all of these stages it still has to be in the right
stage, the idea that we're extending it to all these stages is
limited to the idea of בן שנה. ben shana. Is limited to
the idea that it still has to be one years old, not
that it has to be perfect at those later stages, it just
has to still be one years old. Now the question is, how
could something become more than one year old between the catching of
the blood and the throwing of the blood? Right, it's not like
you waited till the next day. Okay, so that's the next line
of the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara says ומי איכא
מידי דבשעת שחיטה בן שנה ובשעת הולכה וזריקה בן שתים? umi ika
midi debish'at shechitah ben shana ubish'at holachah vezerikah ben shtayim? How can
you have something that at the time of slaughtering it's one year
old and by the time you transport the blood or throw it,
it's now two years old? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא
זאת אומרת שעות פוסלות בקדשים. Amar Rava zot omeret sha'ot poslot bekodshim.
Yes, when you figure out the age of the קרבן, korban, you
don't just go by the day, you go by the hour. Okay,
so it's like this is an interesting question, like by בר מצוה
bar mitzvah or בת מצוה, bat mitzvah, right? A kid is בר
מצוה bar mitzvah you want to know, can he, I don't know,
get an עליה aliyah whatever, today is literally he was born on,
you know, ג' אייר Gimmel Iyar and today is like he was
born at ג' אייר Gimmel Iyar at I don't know, at 11
p... not 11 pm whatever, he's born at ג' אייר Gimmel Iyar
at like 5 pm, okay, and today, right, is
ג' אייר Gimmel Iyar at like 7 am. So he has not
actually gone past
his the line of his birthday. He's not into his next year
yet, he's still finishing up the previous year, if you were to
measure by hours. But the הלכה halachah is by issues of like
בר מצוה bar mitzvah you don't measure by hours, you measure by
days. So
since he's into, right, so I mean you understand, right, that's why
your birthday is like if you were born here, like
אייר, Iyar, if you were born אייר Iyar whatever, you know, whatever
blah blah blah whatever, and you were born on ג' אייר, Gimmel
Iyar, okay, so then you go ahead and go through the whole
year and you come back and now you're at ב' אייר, Bet
Iyar, so you've lived
365 days, I mean it's not because it's a Jewish calendar or
whatever, right, and then when you go into ג' אייר Gimmel Iyar
you're into now the first day of your next year, right? But
that's only if you don't measure by hours. Okay, so by בר
מצוה bar mitzvah issues for example we don't measure by hours, we
measure by days. And since you're on the date of your birth,
it's like you have done one you've lived one full year or
13 full years and now you're into your 14th year. So that's
why the date of your בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, again could be
בת מצוה bat mitzvah as well, but the halachic implications are usually
more discussed by the בר מצוה bar mitzvah case, the date is
the beginning of your next year. By קרבנות korbanot it's not that
way. If you need a קרבן korban to be one year old,
okay, you don't just say the קרבן korban was born, I mean
if it can if it must be one year and not two
years, you don't say, oh, it was born on ג' אייר, Gimmel
Iyar, today is a ג' אייר Gimmel Iyar again, it's two years
old. No, you Say it was born ג' אייר *Gimmel Iyar* at
1:00 PM. Today is ג' אייר *Gimmel Iyar* at 12:00 PM. It's
still only one year old. It's not—it hasn't entered its second year
because we measure by hours. So because of that, it's possible that
you did the שחיטה shechita *shechitah* while it was still one year
old, and then by the time you got to the זריקת הדם
zrikat hadam? *zrikas hadam*, there was a delay and there was a
line or whatever, now it's 1:00 PM and now it actually is
in its second year. So that's where we say that this הלכה
halacha *halakha* of, that it has to still be in its right
state at all of these stages, doesn't apply to the תמים *tamim*,
does not apply to
the unblemished, okay? That only applies to the word that immediately precedes
it, to the בן שנה *ben shanah*. So the conclusion is that
this weird idea that a קרבן korban. *korban* has to remain in
its state not only at the time of שחיטה shechita *shechitah* but
even at the later stages, when it comes to the issue about
unblemished, again, bracketing the fact that its head is cut off, okay,
when it comes to the issue of unblemished, we're limiting to that
of the catching of the blood. Okay? If afterwards the meat gets
destroyed or whatever, that's still okay. As long as at the catching
of the blood, the meat and whatever the body was remained unblemished.
Okay, but what do you need to still be true at the
transporting and the throwing of the blood? Not that it be unblemished,
but that it still be a year old. Okay? So that's this
point of Rava. זאת אומרת שחוש פוסלת בקדשים *zos omeres she-chush poslus
bekadshim*. Okay, אמר רבי אמי *Amar Rabbi Ami*, now, new point. So
that was a very fascinating idea that the state must remain at
the time of קבלה kabala, *kabbalah*, okay, the state of unblemished must
remain at the time of קבלה kabala *kabbalah*. אמר רבי אמי אמר
רבי אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Ami amar Rabbi Elazar*: היא בפנים ורגלה בחוץ
*chi bifnim v'raglah bachutz*, וחתך ואחר כך שחט shechted. כשרה keshera, *v'chatach
v'achar kach shachat kesherah*. Now, remember we said the other important point
to know here with this new topic is that even one drop
of invalid blood is going to be a problem. Remember we said
you have to like pull the knife away so it doesn't, the
blood that hit the knife doesn't fall in, okay, and I mentioned
to you there's a whole question about ביטול *bittul*. So first look
at this tiny little תוספות *Tosafot* at the top of כ"ו עמוד
א' *chaf vav amud aleph*: שחט shechted, ואחר כך חתך פסולה psula,
דדם פסול pasul? אינו בטל ברוב כדמופרך פרשת התערובות דגזרינן גזירה במקדש
*shachat v'achar kach chatach pesulah d'dam pasul eino battel berov kidemoferach parashat
hataarovos d'gazrinan gezeirah bamiktash*. So whether it's Rabbinic, whether it's biblical, any
drop of invalid blood is not going to be nullified and is
going to be a problem. So that's principle number one you have
to know, that even one drop of invalid blood is going to
be a problem. Now, with that in mind, okay, here you've got
your animal,
okay, and here's the line of the עזרה azara. *Azarah*. This is
the עזרה azara *Azarah*, okay, and this is just הר הבית Har
Habayit *Har Habayis*. Okay, and you are going to go ahead and
you're going to שחט shechted *shecht* it, alright? You're going to שחט
shecht *shecht* it like that, okay,
now, and then this guy's going to catch the blood, okay? So
what's going to happen? He's going to catch the blood, the blood
is going to come from the body, okay, all the blood's going
to come from the body, through the cut in the neck and
into the כלי *klee*. Some of the blood is going to come
from here, right? It's going to come from the leg that's outside.
So that blood
is actually invalid. It's blood, the blood that's sort of sanctified and
so on, right, is blood that's in the עזרה azara *Azarah*. Think
about it this way: if you caught the blood and then walked
it out of the עזרה Azara. *Azarah*, you'd invalidate it. That's called
a פסול pasul יוצא yotsei, *psul yotzei*, taking the sanctified thing outside
of the temple precinct. So the blood here that starts outside the
עזרה Azara. *Azarah*, so again, if the animal's alive and walking around,
it doesn't matter. But at the time of שחיטה shechita *shechitah*, when
it sort of like becomes sanctified and now the blood becomes the
blood that you need to use and so on, some of the
blood is being pumped from outside in. This blood is invalid, okay,
and therefore even one drop of it that gets commingled and comes
into the vessel invalidates.
So how do you know whether that's coming in?
You don't. You have to assume that there is a drop of
blood. So if the leg is outside, then you've got to assume
that a drop of blood from the outside came in and it's
invalid. Okay. היא בפנים ורגלה בחוץ *chi bifnim v'raglah bachutz*, one leg
is on the outside, וחתך ואחר כך שחט shecht כשרה *v'chatach v'achar
kach shachat kesherah*. So if what you did is, you cut off
the leg before you did the שחיטה shechita *shechitah*—now of course the
question is how can you cut it off that makes it a
בעל מום baal mum. *baal mum*? So we're going to get to
that. But let's ignore the מום *mum* problem. If you were to
chop off the leg and then שחט shecht. *shecht* it, it would
be okay because then no blood is coming from the outside, ignoring
the fact that it's now a blemished animal, okay? If you chopped
it off right at where it was overstepping the grounds. Okay? שחט
shacht ואחר כך חתך *shachat v'achar kach chatach*, if however you did
the שחיטה shechita *shechitah* and then you chopped off the leg, don't
say, 'Oh, I saved it, because I did the שחיטה shechita *shechitah*,
the part of the animal that was on the outside I'll make
sure not to eat, or whatever I chopped it away, I removed
it, I'm not going to eat that meat, that meat was on
the outside.' That doesn't help you that you chopped it off and
removed the meat afterwards. At the moment of שחיטה shechita *shechitah* some
of the blood came from outside. Invalid. Now the גמרא'ס going to
unpack this. חתך ואחר כך שחט כשרה. Hatach v'achar kach shachat k'sheira.
So if he says, if you cut it first, and now we're
going back. If you cut it first and then you שחט'ד shechted
it, it's okay because you stopped any blood from coming from outside,
but the גמרא gemara says one minute, בעל מום כמקריב, baal mum
kamakriv, it's a blemished chopping off a limb outside that overstepped. אלא
אימא, Ella eima, so the גמרא gemara says fine, let's re-read it.
חתך ואחר כך קיבל כשרה. Hatach v'achar kibel k'sheira. What you did
is, you שחט'ד shechted it,
and
before the blood came out again, I don't know how you're able
to do this instantaneously, but before the blood came out, a second
after you שחט'ד shechted it before it was caught, then you chopped
off the leg. Okay, now of course the point is that maybe
even the split second it took you to chop off the leg,
some of the blood had already traveled up. Let's try to ignore
that possibility. Okay, you שחט'ד shechted it before the blood came out
or was caught, you cut off the leg, so then the actual
catch, the blood that gets caught, is not going to include blood
from outside, and it's okay because you cut it off afterwards so
it's not an issue of a בעל מום. baal mum. The problem
is the teaching we just had, that it has to remain unblemished
even up through the time of קבלה, kabala which is why we're
bringing this in. So the גמרא gemara says אלא אימא חתך ואחר
כך קיבל כשרה קיבל ואחר כך חתך פסולה. eima hatach v'achar kibel
k'sheira kibel v'achar hatach psula. Okay,
but if you caught it and then you chopped it then it's
too late. So then the גמרא gemara says, wait, that doesn't work
either. חתך ואחר כך קיבל כשרה? Hatach v'achar kibel k'sheira? If you
cut it after שחיטה shechitah, before קבלה kabala. it's kosher. How is
that? ואמר רבי זירא הצורם אוזן בכור ואחר כך קיבל דמו פסול.
V'amar Rabbi Zeira hatzum ozen bachur v'achar kibel damo pasul. If you
make a hole in the animal or whatever, it's interesting that it
mentions the word בכור bachur here, because רב זירא Rav Zeira was
הצורם אוזן פר, hatzum ozen par, but בכור bachur is a, it's
a classic discussion in the גמרא gemara about making a, piercing the
hole of the ear of the בכור bachur to make it blemished
and so on. Anyway, and we did extend it to קדשים קלים,
kodshim kalim, but okay. So doesn't רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira say, the
point still is, doesn't רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira say that if you
have a blemish before קבלה kabala. it's invalid, פסול? pasul שנאמר ולקח
מדם הפר הפר שהיה כבר. Shene'emar v'lakach midam hapar hapar she'yehe kvar.
So this answer doesn't work. If you cut it off even after
the שחיטה shechitah you still blemished at the time of קבלה. kabala,
אמר רב חסדא אמר רב אבימי חותך באיבר עד שמגיע לעצם. Amar
Rav Chisda amar Rav Avimi chotech b'eivar ad she'higia l'etzem.
Okay, apparently here's what you can do. You can again, I don't
know how you do such a surgical procedure in the split second
before, well I guess here according to his answer it doesn't have
to be waiting till שעת קבלה. shas kabala.
He says you can cut into the flesh and not make it
a, and not make it a בעל מום. baal mum? Okay, it's
an interesting question right, what defines a בעל מום? baal mum, A
normal type of a wound that's going to heal or whatever. Of
course sometimes you have something that's a מום עובר. mum over. But
without getting into all the הלכות halachos of בעל מום, baal mum,
he basically says if you cut to the bone but you didn't
actually cut the bone, you did this surgical thing, so you cut
all of the flesh around the bone so without cutting the bone,
so that's not a בעל מום, baal mum which sounds pretty surprising
to me, because even if in theory the flesh can heal, it
seems like it now is a בעל מום baal mum or whatever.
Okay, but let's just go with that, that's not a בעל מום
baal mum. because the bone hasn't been cut, but because you've cut
all of the flesh around the bone, no blood is going to
flow up. So he has a way, and now you don't have
to presumably do it between שחיטה shechitah and קבלה. kabbalah He has
a way that you can cut off the flow of blood before
שחיטה shechitah without making it a בעל מום. baal mum Okay, so
that allows us to have that scenario. So if you cut off
the flow of blood without making it a בעל מום before שחיטה
shechitah, then you're okay. But if you did chop it off after
שחיטה shechitah you're not good, because some of the blood came from
outside the עזרה. Azara So let's take a look now at part
two. קיבל ואחר
כך חתך, Kibel v'achar hatach, if you first caught the blood, we're
still using with the קיבל kibel emphasis. Okay, anyway, and then you
cut it פסולה, psula, why? If you chopped it off only after
the קבלה, kabbalah, why is that?
שמע מינה דם המובלע באיברים דם הוא. shemas mina dam hamuvla b'eivarim
dam hu. So the גמרא gemara says one minute though, why should
that blood be a problem? That is blood that is more like
the blood, that's not the main, you know, life blood that defines
the blood
of the animal, you know, the blood that you use for a
קרבן. korban That's more the type of like blood that's present in
the meat, in the capillaries, you know, it's not like in the
main arteries, right, the blood that's coming from there. So that's called
דם המובלע באיברים, dam hamuvla b'eivarim, the blood that's like embedded in
the meat. That's not blood that's used on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So
blood that came from there shouldn't invalidate, right? It's completely irrelevant blood.
Blood that is the דם הנפש, dam hanefesh, that invalidates and gets
mixed up, that invalidates. But blood that, this blood is, could be
like water. If somebody had some water that was outside the עזרה
Azara. and put it in, right, if somebody took some other of
the, I don't know, some urine of the animal and mixed that
was outside the עזרה Azara. and mixed it in it wouldn't invalidate.
So this blood that is not halachically the blood that we're talking
about is irrelevant liquid. So who cares that it gets mixed up?
Okay, so. So should we hear, should we infer from this that
דם המובלע באיברים דם הוא, dam hamuvla beivarim dam hu, that even
that, you know, that capillary blood, the blood in the meat is
blood to use on the מזבח mizbeach if it can create a
problem, if it can invalidate? So the גמרא Gemara says no. דילמא
משום שמנונית, dilma mishum shamnunit, maybe it's the fat. What does this
mean? So רש"י, Rashi, it's a strange idea. רש"י Rashi basically says
what happens is is that the problem is not the blood itself.
The blood itself here is irrelevant. The blood itself here could be
water. The problem is that in the blood is mixed up some
of the fat of the animal. Now I don't know how that
happens, okay? I mean blood always carries nutrients or whatever, you know,
but nevertheless. Anyway the גמרא Gemara imagined that some of the fat
that's outside here is invalid, because part of what are the things
of a קרבן korban, that get invalidated when you bring it outside?
It is the meat can it can be invalidated, it can't be
eaten. The fat can be invalidated, it can't be put on the
altar to be burnt, and the blood can be invalidated that it
can't be put on the altar. Okay, so so the blood here
is not the blood of the altar. The blood from that's in
this leg is irrelevant. What is relevant though
is right if the blood is transporting some of the fat then
in here you get mixed up some invalid fat. Okay, you get
some of again it's biologically I don't understand this at all, but
if we just go with it, if in this blood is mixed
up some פסול pasul part of the קרבן, korban, so פסול pasul
so the blood from the leg is not a פסול pasul part
of the קרבן, korban it's irrelevant, it could be urine. Okay, but
פסול pasul fat or פסול Pasul, meat, invalid because it was on
the outside that's now mixed in the blood somehow invalidates the whole
blood, doesn't let the blood to be put on the altar. Okay,
not exactly clear to me by the way I must say why
that's true either because the fat and the meat you know maybe
you're not allowed to eat them once they go out or you're
not allowed to put the fat to burn on the altar, but
why does its that presence invalidate the blood from being thrown on
the wall of the altar? It would seem like irrelevant, right? If
you took some pork and mixed it in with this blood, don't
eat it but it wouldn't shouldn't make it invalid to put on
the wall of the altar. So if I take some invalid fat
even though it's more
sacrifice related, but if the הלכה halacha is what can you not
do with invalid fat? Don't burn it on the altar. Why should
that prevent me from throwing from putting this blood on the wall
of the altar if it has a little invalid fat mixed into
it? So that's not so clear, but anyway that's what the גמרא
Gemara is assuming. Okay, so דילמא משום
שמנונית. dilma mishum shamnunit. All right. Now we're so that's that's how
we've explained this idea. Certainly the פשט pshat of this is that
it is about the blood, but the גמרא Gemara has a good
question that's not blood that's relevant. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay,
שמע מינה shma mina בשר קדשי קלים שיצא לפני זריקת דם פסול?
basar kodshei kalim sheyatza lifnei zrikat dam pasul?
Now the גמרא's Gemara got another question because since this teaching did
not limit itself to a חטאת, chatat, presumably it's talking even about
קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. Okay, now what's the difference between קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim and קדשים קלים? kodshim kalim? The difference is that קדשי
קדשים, kodshei kodashim, the zone of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is is
it can only be eaten like even the meat of the קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim can only be eaten in the עזרה. azarah, All
right whereas you know here's ירושלים Yerushalayim if you think about these
as like you know concentric whatever, right? Whatever. Okay, הר
הבית and ירושלים. Yerushalayim. קדשים קלים kodshim kalim are the meat like
of a שלמים shlamim or a קרבן פסח korban pesach as a
good קדשים קלים kodshim kalim can be eaten in all of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. All right? קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim can only be eaten in
the עזרה. azarah, Now that's eaten in terms of the meat, right?
But the blood and the fat of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim have
to remain in the עזרה azarah as well. The blood goes on
the altar, the fat goes on the altar, it's only the meat
that gets to be eaten in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Everybody with
me? So let's say after שחיטה shechitah you walked the blood of
the קרבן korban of the קדשים קלים kodshim kalim you walked it
out of the עזרה. azarah. Nobody would debate that you invalidated it
because even though this is a קרבן korban whose meat can be
eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the zone of the blood is the עזרה.
azarah. But that's fine. But here you didn't walk it after the
animal was you know the blood was caught. You walked it out
you know or the blood came from outside right at an early
you know before you even caught the blood? Right? The the problem
is that the blood was coming from outside before it was being
caught. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this. שמע מינה shma mina בשר קדשי קלים שיצא לפני זריקת דם
פסול? basar kodshei kalim sheyatza lifnei zrikat dam pasul? Right that that
should we infer from this that the meat of the קרבן korban
before the throwing of the blood invalidates? If the blood here that's
outside of so here's the scenario to ask okay? Here's sort of
the question we want to... a comparative. What would be, we know
that if you walk the blood outside of the עזרה, azarah. you
invalidate it, even by let's say a שלמים. shlamim. We know that
if you eat the meat outside the עזרה, azarah it's totally okay.
What if you took the meat, now if you took the meat
out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you would invalidate it because that's out of
its zone. What if you took the meat out of the עזרה
azarah before the blood of the קרבן korban, was put on the
wall? Do we say since in the end this meat, and the
meat can't be eaten until the blood goes on the altar, that's
what validates it as a קרבן, korban okay? So do we say
since once the blood goes on the altar,
the meat can be eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, even you know if
you take the meat outside before the blood goes out, it's still
in its right zone and you haven't invalidated it. Or do we
say no, once this thing is made into a קרבן by שחיטה,
shechitah its zone is only the עזרה. azarah And the only thing
that allows the meat to be eaten in all of ירושלים Yerushalayim
is, you know, once it's become the blood gets put on and
it's sort of becomes a accepted and a valid sacrifice. But in
that period between the שחיטה Shechitah, and the putting of the blood,
the entire zone has to be the עזרה. azarah, Now you're still
sort of working it up as a sacrifice and that precinct is
only the עזרה. azarah. So that's the question: between the שחיטה shechitah
and the זריקה, zrikah, right? Can you actually, if you took the
meat outside, you know, outside of the עזרה azarah in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
would you invalidate the meat? Got the question? So the גמרא Gemara
says let's try to infer it from here. The question is, is
do we say from the time of שחיטה Shechitah until זריקה, zrikah,
everything has to remain in the עזרה azarah itself? And here it
seems like it does, that even blood coming from outside is a
problem. So it seems to be that, you know, even by קדשים
קלים, Kodshim Kalim, the entire zone remains in the עזרה azarah, until
the blood is sprinkled. And only then can the meat be taken
out. Of course here we're talking about blood and here we're talking
about meat. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says back.
שמע מינה, Shmas Minah, should I infer from this that בשר קדשים
קלים שיצא לפני זריקת הדם פסול? basar Kodshim Kalim sheyatza lifnei zrikat
hadam pasul? So the גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא בקדשי קדשים, dilma
bekodshei kodshim, maybe we're talking about the Holy of Holies, who said
we were talking about something like a שלמים, shlamim, okay?
Now,
excuse me. So I have to tell you that it's interesting that
the גמרא Gemara went, oh I know why, I'm sorry. I was
getting hooked up on, I was getting hung up on like what
type of a comparison is that. Here it's the blood, blood can
never go outside the עזרה, azarah. how are you comparing it to
the question of meat? I forgot that the גמרא's Gemara answer was
the problem here isn't the blood. Remember the גמרא Gemara said that
this blood isn't really a blood, what did the גמרא Gemara say
the problem here was? The fat. Well the fat, the שמנונית, shamnus,
now שמנונית shamnus is different than חלב. chelev. שמנונית shamnus is the,
yeah I apologize, I was before saying it as if it was
חלב. chelev. חלב chelev is the fat that gets offered on the
altar. שמנונית shamnus is the type of normal fat you get when
you get your steak, you know it's the fat that actually you're
allowed to eat, okay? חלב chelev is suet. Most פרום frum Jews
have no idea what the heck suet is. חלב chelev is the
fatty stuff that's embedded in the meat, in the meat itself. The
חלב chelev that's put on the altar is like the free-floating fat
that so when you cut up an animal you see this like
free-floating fat, it's not embedded in the meat itself. Okay, so שמנונית
shamnus is the stuff that's embedded. So the גמרא's Gemara answer before,
that what you get that's invalid is the שמנונית, shamnus, the fattiness
of the meat, okay? That's what it is, not the fat that's
on the altar. The fattiness of the meat that got mixed up
in the blood. The גמרא Gemara says well one minute, if this
is קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodshim then this is just meat that's outside
the עזרה. azarah The fattiness of the meat is like meat. So
why is meat outside of an עזרה azarah. a problem? Does this
tell us that meat outside the עזרה azarah, is a problem before
זריקת הדם? zrikat hadam And the answer is no, because maybe what
we're talking about is קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodshim and קדשי קדשים Kodshei
Kodshim can never go outside the עזרה, azarah? even the meat. But
maybe if we're talking about קדשים קלים, Kodshim Kalim, maybe this would
not be a problem because the only thing that transfers in is
the fattiness of the meat and the fattiness of the meat, maybe
that's not a problem even before זריקת הדם zrikat hadam that the
meat itself is outside the עזרה. azarah And
we
said the blood
itself.
Yes, but again that's what I got mixed up with. It is,
but the blood is irrelevant since that's not the blood. Okay? So
one more time, I apologize for the confusion. The גמרא's Gemara question
was does this show us that the, why is this blood an
issue? This blood is not the life blood, it's the blood that's
embedded in the meat, why does it invalidate? And the answer is
it's not the blood that's invalid, it's the blood that transports the
שמנונית, shamnus, the fattiness of the meat, okay? I just said why
do I care that there's פסול Pasul meat in my blood, why
should that invalidate the blood? But that's the גמרא's Gemara assuming if
the, if the meat is invalid as an invalid you know... part
of a sacrifice, the fatness of the meat, which is like the
meat, and it gets mixed up with the blood, you can't use
the blood on the altar. But then the גמרא Gemara says, but
one minute, if it's just meat, and this is קדשי קלים, kodshei
kalim, why is that a problem? Should we infer from this that
the meat of a of like a שלמים shlamim that goes out
before זריקת הדם zrikat hadam. becomes invalid? Because that's what you have,
meat that's out before זריקת הדם. Zrikas HaDam. In the end, the
meat's going to be able to be eaten everywhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
And the גמרא Gemara's answer is, no, maybe actually that would be
valid if this were קדשי קלים. kodshei kalim. We're talking about קדשי
קדשים, kodshei kodashim, we're talking about like a חטאת, chatat, and by
those things, yes, anything of it that goes out of the עזרה
azarah, is invalid because that has to, that's precinct remains the
עזרה. azarah, Alright, everybody got that? Good, as much as you're going
to get it. Okay. Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. קדשי קדשים שחיטתם בצפון וקיבל דמם בכלי
שרת בצפון. Kodshei kodashim shechitatam batzafon v'kibel damam bichlei sharet batzafon. So
this, so the קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, חטאת chatat and an עולה,
olah, by the way, just in case, we might as well put
this up in case people don't have this clear. Okay.
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and קדשי קלים. kodshei kalim.
Okay, קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is A: עולה, olah, חטאת, chatat, and
an אשם. asham. Basic common denominator is they can't leave the precincts
of the עזרה, azarah, okay, even when you eat the meat or
whatever. And קדשי קלים kodshei kalim is basically, usually abbreviate it like
that,
קדשי קלים kodshei kalim is basically שלמים shlamim and everything that's like
a שלמים: shlamim: בכור, bechor,
מעשר, maaser, פסח, pesach, etc. Where do you think, by the way,
you would put a מנחה? mincha?
Any guesses? Can מנחה mincha be eaten outside of the עזרה? azarah,
Who eats a מנחה? mincha? If it can be eaten by the,
point here is ירושלים Yerushalayim
and ישראל Yisrael
can eat it,
and this is עזרה azarah. and כהנים. kohanim. Who eats a מנחה?
mincha? Only the כהנים kohanim and only in the עזרה, azarah. so
מנחה mincha goes here as well. Okay? So that's the basic difference.
Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan.
קדשי קדשים, Kodshei kodashim, so all the קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, שחיטתם
בצפון, shechitatam batzafon, you slaughtered at the north of the עזרה, azarah.
וקיבל דמם בכלי שרת בצפון, v'kibel damam bichlei sharet batzafon, and you
catch the blood with a holy vessel at in the north. Okay.
עמד בדרום והושיט ידו לצפון ושחט. Amad badarom v'hoshit yado latzafon v'shachat.
Now you've got, see this lets me use all of my drawing
ability. Okay, here's your
בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash,
north, east. Okay,
whatever. Got your אולם, Ulam, here's your מזבח. mizbeach.
This is your line. There's actually a question of exactly whether the
מזבח mizbeach crossed the line or not, anyway. So קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim you do at the north. So here's where you're going to
do your קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, okay, you're going to do it
right here, okay. Here's your animal. על ירך המזבח צפונה. Al yerech
hamizbeach tzafonah. Okay.
Now what you did was, where were we, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
קדשי קדשים, Kodshei kodashim, שחיטה, Shechitah, and kibel and you have to
catch the blood in the north. The guy who's catching the blood
can't be standing here and catching it, he has to catch it
over here, okay. That's where he's got to do the שחיטה Shechitah,
and the and the catching of the blood in the north. עמד
בדרום, Amad badarom, okay,
עמד בדרום והושיט ידו לצפון ושחט. Amad badarom v'hoshit yado latzafon v'shachat.
Now the guy is standing right over the line over here and
he is reaching with his arm and doing the שחיטה shechita and
the animal and the catching of the blood are in the north,
but the guy is in the south. Okay? So does the only
thing that defines it where the animal is or does it also
define where the שוחט shochet is? Okay. שחיטה זו כשרה. Shechitah zo
kesherah. That's valid. It's about the animal, okay, the animal has to
be in the north, not the שוחט. shochet. קיבל קבלתו פסולה. Kibel
kabbalato psulah. If however the catching of the blood was in the
was in the south, that's not good. The שחיטה shechitah, and the
קבלה kabbalah have to be in the north.
הכניס ראשו ורובו כאילו נכנס כולו. Hichnis rosho v'rubo k'ilu nichnas kulo.
Now let's say he and the majority of him, let me just
check רש"י Rashi here. Oh
right,
in terms of the catching of the blood, because it's not just
where is the vessel, the כהן kohen who catches the blood has
to also be in the north. Okay. Let's say the כהן kohen
is in the south, right here's the line, the כהן kohen's in
the south, but
his head and the majority of his body are in the north,
that's okay. שחיטה, shechitah the whole person can be in the in
the south, okay, because שחיטה shechitah it's not about, and one of
the reasons is who can be שוחט? shochet? Is it only a
כהן kohen that can be שוחט? shochet? No, anybody can be שוחט.
shochet. So therefore, we have less focus on the person and the
act of the שחיטה shechitah, etcetera to satisfy a lot of the
requirements because if it's not done by a non-כהן, Kohen, it means
there's generally more latitude, it's not seen as an עבודה avoda in
the same way. So the שחיטה, shechitah the whole guy can be.
The קבלה, kabbalah not only the vessel, but the כהן Kohen doing
the act of קבלה kabbalah, has to be here in the north.
But if his body and the majority, his head and the majority
of his body is, even though it's interesting, his feet are planted
in the south. You might think you define where you are by
where your feet are planted, I think this is a real חידוש.
chiddush. But no, as long as the majority of your body, you
know, and your head are in the north, it's like you the
כהן Kohen is in the north and it's valid.
Is a non-כהן Kohen allowed in that area?
Technically, yes. I mean, it wouldn't usually happen, but technically, yes. Okay.
Now, okay.
קיבל קבלתו פסולה. kibel kibalaso pesulah. הכניס ראשו ורובו כאילו לא נכנס.
hichnis rosho verubo ke-ilu lo nichnas. פרכסה ויצאה לחוץ וחזרה פסולה. pirchasa
ve-yatsah lachuts ve-chazarah pesulah. Now, let's say the animal, wait,
I'm sorry, I skipped a line. Did I skip a line? I
skipped a line.
פרכסה ויצאה לדרום וחזרה כשירה. pirchasa ve-yatsah ldarom ve-chazarah kesherah. Let's say
after you shechted it, the animal thrashed around and it, you know,
and it, the whole body moved into the south, and then it
moved back. It doesn't even have to move back, the point is,
it's kosher. Once it's shechted and the blood was caught in the
north, you really don't care if the animal moves into the south.
It can't go out of the עזרה, azarah. right? But it can
go anywhere in the עזרה, azarah right? So that's okay. Now, קדשים
קלים, kodashim kalim, now how about lighter sacrifices? שחיטתן בפנים, shechitasan bifnim,
there it doesn't have to be in the north, it just has
to be in the עזרה. azarah, וקיבל דמם בכלי שרת בפנים, ve-kibel
damam bichli shares bifnim, and the blood has to be caught. Again,
the כהן Kohen has to be standing and catching the blood in
the עזרה. azarah. There it's not about the north, it's about the
whole עזרה. azarah עמד בחוץ והכניס ידו לפנים ושחט שחיטתו כשירה. amad
bachuts ve-hichnis yado lifnim ve-shachat shechitaso kesherah.
Similarly, if the guy is standing, you don't even have to be
standing, this is a big חידוש. chiddush. Once we're not requiring a
כהן, Kohen, the person doing the act of שחיטה, shechitah. the same
way he can be a non-כהן, Kohen, can be outside the עזרה.
azarah. If you had a long enough knife, the guy could be
standing in New York, okay, if you had a five thousand mile
knife and shechting an animal in the עזרה azarah. and it could
be kosher. Once you don't need a כהן, Kohen, it's so, it's
not, if the person doesn't have to be like sanctified, as it
were, then he doesn't have to be on sanctified ground either. The
animal has to be in the עזרה, azarah, but the person can
be outside the עזרה. azarah? קיבל, kibel, if of course the person
is outside the עזרה azarah, and catching the blood, קבלתו פסולה, kibalaso
pesulah, it's invalid, obviously, because once you need a כהן, Kohen, it
all has to be in the עזרה. azarah. For קדשי קדשים, kodshei
kodashim, the כהן Kohen has to be in the north. It's not
enough that he's like, you know, that he's, that the blood is
caught in the north, he has to be in the north. And
for קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, he has to be in the עזרה.
azarah. He can't be leaning over. However, remember we said by the
north, if him and the majority of his body leaned over, it
was valid. What about in the case of the קבלת הדם? kabbalas
hadam? If he was outside the עזרה, azarah but he and the
majority of his body leaned over, what would be the, you know,
and crossed the line, would that be okay? It works for the
north, does it work for the עזרה? azarah, So that's the next
line, it says, where were we, הכניס ראשו ורובו כאילו לא נכנס.
hichnis rosho verubo ke-ilu lo nichnas.
Here
you and the majority of your body doesn't work. It matters where
your feet are planted. Okay, hear the difference. Now why, it makes
sense why there's a difference, okay, because fundamentally, think about, maybe one
way to sort of think about this is, remember how we talked
about how the כהן Kohen has to be barefoot and touching the
floor of the עזרה, azarah, and that sanctifies him and makes him
part of the apparatus of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and so
on. So he has to be standing in the עזרה. azarah, Anything
that requires a כהן Kohen requires him to stand in the עזרה.
azarah, So even if we say that he is situated when he
leans over, if he's in the עזרה azarah and in the south
and leans over and it's the majority of his body, then we
could say he's situated in the north and that works for the
north versus the south. But in the issue of the עזרה, azarah
it doesn't matter where he's situated. Even if we say his place
is in the עזרה, azarah since his feet are outside the עזרה,
Azara. he is not, his feet are not touching the floor of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, he's not connected to the apparatus of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and in that case actually when it
comes to the עזרה, Azara, it's not enough that he leans over.
His feet have to be planted in the עזרה Azara itself. Okay,
so now it says like this, where were we, פרכסה ויצאה לחוץ
וחזרה פסולה. pirchaso ve-yatsah lachuts ve-chazarah pesulah.
If the animal after shechting went out of the, went out of
the עזרה Azara and then came back in, it's invalid because when
it went out of the עזרה Azara it actually was יוצא, it
went out and it got invalid. Now the question: what do you
mean? This is meat of a שלמים, shelamim, who cares that it
went out? and thrashing around after it was שחט. This is meat
that can be eaten in all of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? So we'll
get back to that. But here the point is if it thrashes
around from north to south after it was שחט, who cares? It
still stayed in the עזרה. Azara. This, you know, not a problem.
But if it was קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim and it thrashed around
after it was שחט and it went outside, that would invalidate it.
So we'll see why, because the meat can be eaten outside. But
remember, it's before זריקת הדם. Zrikas HaDam Yes?
Does that mean that the altar is movable? Like, why wouldn't they
put the altar in a place where these things are just not
going to happen?
Well, the altar is not movable, but if all of the קדשי
קדשים Kodshei Kodashim are taking place here, then you might want to,
you know, have the קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim take place here. You
know, it's true, you normally would not have it go right up
against the edge of the עזרה, Azara. right? You'd want to, you
know, in general, you'd want there to be a buffer zone. Actually,
what the גמרא Gemara says is, is that the גמרא Gemara says
that these first eleven אמות Amos is
עזרת ישראל, Ezras Yisroel, and here's where the ישראלים Yisraelim came that
they brought their קרבנות Korbanos and they usually didn't cross that line,
and the כהנים Kohanim were here. So that would normally be a
buffer zone. I mean, even if you would שחט it, you know,
way up front, it would usually be eleven אמות Amos away. So
to thrash twenty-two feet or whatever it would be, would be a
lot. Okay, but no, here you would centralize all of the קדשי
קדשים. Kodshei Kodashim. So when you're doing the שלמים, Shelamim, you're doing
it in the other area. So it—anyway, it doesn't matter, it's a
hypothetical. What would be if it would thrash around and get itself
outside? Okay, so but the question is what's the problem? This is
meat of a שלמים. Shelamim. Okay, so anyway, let's take a look.
Where were we? So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא וכו' שמע מינה
בשר קדשי קלים שיצא לפני זריקת דם פסולים. Pshita etc. Shema mina
basar Kodshei Kalim sheyatza lifnei Zrikas Dam psulim. So this is, so
okay, this גמרא Gemara says that seems to answer our previous question,
that meat of a
קדשי Kodshei קדשים—קדשים קלים that left the עזרה Azarah. before the blood
is invalid. Because why else, what else does it mean to say
that the animal becomes invalid if it thrashes around? Okay, it's a
שלמים. Shelamim. Who cares that it thrashed around and is outside the
עזרה Azarah, now? What's invalid? So it seems like the meat itself
can become invalid out of the עזרה Azarah. before the throwing of
the blood. Okay, so is that true? הגמרא HaGemara says no. דילמא
באליה ויותרת הכבד ושתי הכליות. Dilma b'alyah v'yoseres hakaved u'shtei haklayos. This
is why I got mixed up before, because here the גמרא Gemara
is talking about the חלב. Cheilev. No, because in the קדשי—in the
animal, in the שלמים, Shelamim, there is stuff that has to always
remain in the עזרה. Azarah What is it? The stuff that gets
burnt on the altar. Okay, it's the kidneys, it's the fat tail,
okay, that type of stuff. That, even of a קדשים קלים, Kodashim
Kalim even of a שלמים, Shelamim, because that is to be burnt
on the altar, that always gets invalidated if it's removed out. So
when we say if the animal thrashed around and went out, it's
invalid, it might not mean the meat is invalid. Maybe you could
go ahead and eat the meat, okay? Because the meat is going
to be eaten in all of ירושלים Yerushalayim anyway. So maybe it's
not a problem that it went outside before the blood was thrown.
What you can't do with this animal is put the fat on
the altar, because the fat has to remain in the עזרה. Azarah.
The fat never has an allowance to go outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
That's only the meat.
Alright? Looks like you want to ask a question.
Yes? Right. When you said they could maybe eat the meat anyway,
what are you eating? You're eating an
invalid—it's not a sacrifice.
No, yes it is. When we say פסול, Pasul actually a good
point. Okay, פסולים Psulim here does not mean—well, it might depend a
little bit on the debate question about whether you can be do
זריקת הדם Zrikas HaDam, if the fat—but but assuming that you can
still do זריקת הדם, Zrikas HaDam, so okay, you do זריקת הדם,
you don't offer—what's פסול Pasul. is the fat. The fat is פסול
Pasul to offer on the altar, but not that the sacrifice is
פסול. pasul, Right, thank you. You know, here the problem is the
blood remains okay and you can still go ahead with the blood.
Okay, but yes, that's a good point. פסול here does not mean
the whole sacrifice gets thrown out. Let's just try to finish to
the משנה. Mishna. Oh my God, I didn't realize time got away
from us. בעי מיניה אבוה דשמואל משמואל. Bei minei avua d'Shmuel miShmuel.
So the father of שמואל Shmuel asked from שמואל Shmuel the following
question. היו בפנים ורגליהן בחוץ מהו. Hayu bifnim v'ragleihen bachutz mahu. Let's
say, okay, the animal is on the inside and the foot is
on the outside, which seems to be the question that we asked
before. So,
but the question here
is—okay, why is this different than the question that we asked before?
Hold on.
Oh, because before what we said was—remember, before we said—one
minute—yeah, before—so the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes tries to answer this question.
Okay, but meaning before we said that that actually was a problem,
the blood brings the fattiness etc. etc. But at least the גמרא
Gemara before had some solution. Like you could cut the leg and
do the שחיטה shechitah and it wouldn't be a problem. So he
wants to know, are you allowed to do this לכתחילה? L'chatchila? To
שחט it with a leg on the outside. The obvious answer should
be no because the whole point before was pointing out the problems
with a leg being on the outside. Anyway, מהו? mahu? אמר ליה
כתיב. amar lei ksiv. ויובא לה' עד שתהא כולה בפנים *V'yuvam laHashem,
ad shetei kula bifnim*. It all has to be on the inside.
Alright, so that's the whole animal has to be standing on the
inside. It seems like it's a different approach than the previous one.
The previous one had the whole problem of bringing the fatness, bringing
the meat getting mixed up, you know, etc., and invalidating the blood
because there was some little טריפה *treif* stuff that got mixed up
into it. This seems to be answering the same question and saying
it's a problem from a different perspective. Not because some of it
is being brought, but the definition that requires that it be standing
in the עזרה azarah, *Azara* or that it be standing in the
north, right, that is something that is about the fine- the whole
animal, not just part of the animal. Because you could ask the
question here, right, let's say a little part of the animal was
in the south and most of it was in the north, right,
then it wouldn't have this issue about stuff coming from outside the
בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. When we say the animal has to be
standing, do we mean all four legs of the animal or even
like three legs of the animal? Okay, so it's a different question
than the question before. This is relevant even to the north-south issue.
And the answer is ויובאו לה' *V'yuvau laHashem* bring them עד שתהא
כולה לפנים *ad shetei kula lifnim*. Although here he is emphasizing the
issue of in- before God, in the עזרה azarah. *Azara*. Alright, so
it's the same issue as question as before, but the concern is
different. The concern is not the blood transferring the fatness, the concern
is that the whole animal has to be present before God, and
therefore all four legs of the animal have to be present. Now,
תלה ושחט veshachat מהו Mahu? *Tala v'shachat mahu*? And now we get
to some fun questions, let's try to push through here to the
משנה *Mishnah*. Okay, let's say you had the animal suspended, you know,
now they're talking about the whole thing with meat and hoist- hoist
and shackle, you know, and how cruel this is to the animals
and so on. So let's say you had were doing this. You
had the whole animal hanging in mid-air and you did the שחיטה
shechitah *Shechita*. So the animal was in the north or was in
the עזרה azarah, *Azara*, but as opposed to the question about the
feet of the כהן Kohen, *Kohen* touching the ground, like do you
need the feet of the animal touching the ground? Okay, so תלה
ושחט מהו *Tala v'shachat mahu*? אמר ליה Amar leih, *Amar
lei*, so Shmuel said to his father, כשרה *Keshera*, that should be
kosher, why not? אמר ליה Amar leih, *Amar lei*, אשתבשת *Ishtabashta*, you
have made a mistake. בעינן שחיטה shechitah על ירך al yerech. וליכא
*Beinan shechita al yerech v'leika*. This is talking about קדשי קדשים Kodshei
Kodashim *kodshei kodashim*, so it says על ירך Al yerech המזבח צפונה
*Al yerech hamizbei'ach tzfona* by the- by the side of the altar.
So the word al, like juxtaposed to the side, somehow means not
suspended in mid-air. You could be suspended in mid-air and still, you
know, you know, the altar was pretty high. Okay, but nevertheless somehow
it's reading this sense of al, like the same way the altar
is planted on the ground, and this is juxtaposed to the altar,
this is at least קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim *kodshei kodashim*, it's on
the north, okay, that has to also be on the ground. נתלה
ושחט מהו *Nitla v'shachat mahu*? So it's going to be funny, like
Shmuel's going to try to give the answer to the immediately previous
question and it's always going to be wrong. Okay, so first he
said כשרה *Keshera* and his father said no, that's פסולה *psula*, it's
not next to- considered by the altar. Then he says what happens
if the כהן Kohen *Kohen* was suspended in mid-air and did the
שחיטה shechitah *Shechita*? מהו *Mahu*? אמר ליה *Amar lei*, פסולה *Psula*. So
he said to him, it's- that would be פסולה *psula*, because he's
trying to work off of the last answer. So אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, אשתבשת *Ishtabashta*, no, you've made a mistake, a mistake, שחיטה shechitah
על ירך al yerech, ולא שוחט shochet על ירך al yerech. *Shechita
al yerech v'lo shochet al yerech*. Okay, the שחיטה shechitah. *Shechita* has
to be on the side, again, the animal has to be on
the side of the altar, but the שוחט shochet *shochet* doesn't have
to be situated on the side of the altar, and we know
that because the שוחט shochet *shochet* can even be in the south.
He doesn't have to be in the north. And why do his
feet not have to be touching the עזרה azarah. *Azara*? Because he
doesn't have to be a כהן Kohen *Kohen* because we're talking about
שחיטה shechitah *Shechita*. Okay, so the animal, it's just like the point
before, the animal has to be situated in the north, feet on
the ground, not the שוחט shochet *shochet*.
Only the other parts of the עבודה *avodah* he have to have
his feet on the ground.
Yes, absolutely, because this- exactly, because this is about שחיטה shechitah *Shechita*.
Okay, now, נתלה וקיבל Nitlah v'kibeil. מהו *Nitla v'kibeil mahu*, which is
what we're about to do. So now he's going to go again.
So the- the answer here was kosher to the immediate one. Let's
say the animal was suspended and the blood was caught. So after
the שחיטה shechitah. *Shechita* with the animal's feet on the ground, you
hoisted the animal up and caught the blood with the animal suspended
in mid-air. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, כשרה *Keshera*. So he's again working
off of the last answer. So he said, it's kosher, right? Isn't
that right? Don't you want me to say kosher? אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, no, אשתבשת *Ishtabashta*, you got it wrong again. אין דרך שירות
ein derech sheirut? בכך *Ein derech sheirus bekach*. Okay, I'm sorry.
Oh, I'm sorry. It was נתלה *Nitla*. I'm sorry. נתלה וקיבל מהו
*Nitla v'kibeil mahu*. The כהן Kohen *Kohen* is suspended in mid-air. Okay,
if the כהן Kohen, *Kohen* is suspended in mid-air and he catches
the blood, so Shmuel said it's kosher. And he said no, that's
not ושרת, that's not a normal way of serving, you know, your
master with being suspended in mid-air. Okay, that only a problem by
catching the blood. So when it's שחיטה, shechitah you don't need the
feet touching the ground, you don't need a כהן, Kohen, you don't
need the שוחט shocheit to be in the north, you don't even
need the שוחט to be in the עזרה. azarah. So the שוחט
could be suspended in mid-air, it doesn't have to be דרך שירות,
derech sheirut, because שחיטה shechitah. is not about all of this question
of the כהן Kohen and the process and so on. Okay? So
we don't need it to be דרך שירות. derech sheirut. By catching
the blood, if the כהן Kohen is in the south or suspended
in mid-air or wherever he is, that's a problem. That requires כהונה,
kehunah, and there you have to, everything has to be proper. Now
what I want to know is why did it just say אין
דרך שירות? It should say his feet aren't touching the ground, and
that's a problem, right, that you need directly to be touching the
ground, that's what we learned before to sanctify. But it's all related,
okay? Once you're dealing with קבלה kabbalah. onward, you're dealing with כהונה
kehunah and you're dealing with much stronger requirements. So there, you know,
he's got to be situated, maybe he could be leaning over, but
he's got to be situated in the north and he can't be
suspended in mid-air. All right, so let's just wrap this up. Now,
last question: טלה וקיבל מהו? tolo vekibel mahu?
That's what I jumped to. If the animal is suspended and you
caught, you the כהן Kohen, were standing on the ground and you
caught the blood from the animal, then the animal was suspended, what's
the story? אמר ליה, פסולה, he said פסול, again working off of
the last answer. אמר ליה, אישתבשא, ishtabasha, got that wrong too. שחיטה
על ירך ולא קבלה על ירך. Shechitah al yerech velo kabbalah al
yerech.
The שחיטה shechitah it says על ירך המזבח צפון, al yerech hamizbe'ach
tzafon, and the animal has to be situated by the altar, but
the קבלה, kabbalah the animal does not have to be situated by
the altar. Okay? So the basic point is that the animal's feet
has to be on the ground at the time of the שחיטה,
shechitah, not at the time of the קבלה. kabbalah That's a special
thing he learns out from על ירך. The כהן, Kohen when you
require a כהן, Kohen the כהן Kohen can't be suspended from קבלה
kabbalah. on. And then the כהן kohen has to be in the
north, etc., etc. When you don't require a כהן, kohen, okay, then
the person can actually be suspended in mid-air, שחיטה shechitah can even
be outside of the
עזרה, azarah, etc., etc. Okay, so now it says like this: Oh,
okay.
Where were we?
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, בקדשי קדשים כולם פסולות בר מנטלה. bekodshei kodashim
kulam psulot bar minitlah.
So when it comes to בקדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, like
חטאת, chatas, they're all invalid except for the case where the כהן
kohen's is suspended, or whoever's suspended, ושחט and does the שחיטה. shechitah
Okay? Because he actually is stricter. He says yes, שחיטה you can
always, it doesn't matter, right, what where the guy is, because שחיטה
again, so the שחיטה the guy could be suspended, but everything else
your feet have to be on the ground. Even for the, even
when you're catching the blood of the animal, the animal has to
be on the ground as well, even when it's the blood is
being caught, not just when it's being שחט. So he's more מחמיר
machmir than שמואל's Shmuel father. He says
for the catching of the blood as well, the feet of the
animal have to be on the ground. על ירך applies both to
the שחיטה and the
catching. בקדשים קלים כולם כשרות בר מנטלה וקיבל. Bekodshim kalim kulam kesherot
bar minitlah vekibel. By קדשים קלים, Kodashim Kalim, okay, you don't require
the feet of the animal to be on the ground, because you
don't have על ירך, and you don't require the שוחט to be
on the ground because that doesn't require כהונה. kehunah. The only time
the feet have to be on the ground is the feet of
the כהן kohen catching the blood, because again, from the time of
קבלה kabbalah? on, you've got to have your feet touching the floor
of the עזרה. azarah, All right. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now רבא
Rava says, מהי שנא טלה וקיבל בקדשים קלים דכשירה דאויר פנים כפנים
דמי? mai shna tolo vekibel bekodshim kalim dekshera de'avir pnim kepnim dami?
Why do you say when the animal is suspended, you know, and
you catch it, that's כשרה, when you, you know, so, because being
in the air space of the עזרה azarah, is being in the
עזרה. azarah? So בקדשי קדשים נמי אויר צפון כצפון דמי? bekodshei kodashim
nami avir tzafon ketzafon dami? So when the animal is suspended, it
should also be good for קבלה. kabbalah, Again, he's going back to
שמואל's Shmuel point. Why is suspended, the suspending of the animal a
problem at the time of קבלה? kabbalah. It's in the air space.
There's no הלכה that the feet of the animal have to touch
the ground. The only time we might do that is by the
שחיטה because of על ירך. That דרשה drasha of ושחטו אותו על
ירך veshachato oto al yerech is only by the שחיטה. Fundamentally, the
issue is the כהן's kohen, feet are on the ground, not the,
not the animal's feet are on the ground. So air space is
okay. And if you want to invalidate when the animal's suspended, you
need a special פסוק, pasuk, and that פסוק pasuk is only by
the שחיטה on the north. אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, so
רבא Rava goes back to what שמואל's Shmuel father
said: בין קדשי קדשים בין קדשים קלים כשרות. bein kodshei kodashim bein
kodshim kalim kesherot. It's כשר kasher when the animal is
suspended, בר מנטלה ושחט בקדשי קדשים. bar minitlah veshachat bekodshei kodashim. The
one time the animal being suspended doesn't work is if the animal
is, it's by קדשי קדשים Kadshei Kadashim where it's צפונה על ירך
המזבח, tzafona al yerech hamizbe'ach, like שמואל's Shmuel father, where it says
north by the side of the altar, then... That is the meaning
that the שחיטה not only be at the north but that the
feet of the animal be planted on the ground as well. So
it's only by קדשי קדשים Kadshei Kadashim. and only by שחיטה. And
the other thing that's invalid is נתלה וקיבל. If the כהן kohen's
is suspended when he catches the blood. Since from the time of
catching the blood on it requires a כהן, kohen so therefore the
כהן's kohen, feet have to be on the ground. So if the
כהן kohen is suspended, בין בקדשי קדשים בין בקדשי קלים, bein be-kadshei
kadashim bein be-kadshei kalim, that would be invalid because that is something
that requires a כהן, קבלה, kabbalah and therefore even by שלמים shelamim
his feet have to be on the ground. All right, very last
point. בעי מיניה רב ירמיה מרבי זירא. Ba'ei minei Rav Yirmeyah me-Rabbi
Zeira. Rav Yirmeyah asked Rabbi Zeira: הוא בפנים וציציתו בחוץ מהו? Hu
bifnim v'tzitzito bachutz mahu? The כהן's on the inside, okay, but his
ציצית—doesn't tzitzit literally mean his ציצית, tzitzit, it's his ponytail
essentially—is on the outside. Okay. So does the כהן have to be...
his feet are totally planted on the floor of the עזרה, azarah
but part of his body is outside the עזרה. azarah. You could
say let's say his elbow's outside the עזרה, azarah right? When he's
doing the שחיטה he moves his elbow outside the עזרה. azarah, But
we're making it even more trivial, just his hair is outside of
the עזרה. Is that a problem for, you know, you know, now
outside, that's not by שחיטה. שחיטה you could be outside. For קבלה.
kabbalah קבלה kabbalah you need to be in the עזרה, you know,
that's what we're saying, you can't be suspended in the air even
by קדשי קדשים. What about if you're doing the קבלה kabbalah and
you're fully inside and your ponytail is outside? Okay. שחיטה, you want
to be in midair, you want to fly in the air, you
want to be in New York with a super long knife and
שחט or whatever, fine. שחיטה doesn't matter. But from קבלה kabbalah onwards
we need you in the עזרה, your feet planted in the עזרה,
not to be suspended. What if your ponytail at the time of
קבלה is outside of the עזרה? Okay. So what's the story? מהו?
אמר ליה לאו אמרת בבואם אל אהל מועד עד שיבוא כולו לפנים?
Amar lei lav amarta bevo'am el ohel mo'ed ad she-yavo kulo lifnim?
You said the animal has to be fully in the עזרה and
you said כולו, kulo, even one leg can't be outside, it has
to be fully present. הכא נמי בבואם, Hacha nami bevo'am, talking about
the כהנים, kohanim, when they come אל אהל מועד, el ohel mo'ed,
עד שיבוא כולו לאהל מועד. ad she-yavo kulo l'ohel mo'ed. He has
to fully be present. Okay. So anytime you need the כהן, you
need him to be, you know, when you need a כהן from
קבלה onwards, his feet have to be on the ground, he can't
be suspended in midair. If it has to be in the north,
he's got to be in the north, maybe he could be leaning
into the north, but he's got to be in the north, okay,
he cannot be in midair and even a little hair and even
like a hair can't be outside. He has to be 100% fully
in the עזרה. There's a nice obviously דרשה drasha in there somewhere
and you have to be fully present. You can't be a little
bit your mind somewhere else. You know, if you're there in the
עזרה and doing the service, you have to be 100% fully present.
But again, שחיטה has a lot of allowances. The שוחט doesn't have
to be in the north, he doesn't have to be in the
עזרה, he could be suspended in midair, etc., etc. Okay, we'll end
with this for now.